[SPEAKER_01]: Well, let's do it in the example I already gave.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the perceptions of the forest that you can use to establish your mind so you're not bothered by anything in the village, it's not the actual perceiving of the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I'm perceiving that I'm in the forest, I'm in the forest, which is usually how people practice their meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have perception of the forest when you're not in the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how it's done rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it's not actual perceiving on the level of your eye, nose, smell, taste and touch and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind perceives the mood of the forest, the context of the forest, from when you were in the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if your mind is established upon the context, which literally means circumstances and environment,
[SPEAKER_01]: That provides a basis for more particular action.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, despite that you're in the village, your mind refuses to abandon the context of the greater forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means then, your time in the village, it's only going to be minimal for whatever necessary reason, but it won't be uprooting the general context of the perception of the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I live in the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why Buddha said, if you develop perception of the forest, if you develop context of the forest, no particular action done in the town or whatever else, will be able to affect you.
[SPEAKER_01]: No particular sight, sound, smell, taste, touches from the town or a village will be able to affect you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mind still perceives itself on the basis of the context of the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you get careless, you forget that, you start giving in to particular sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches in the village, you drop off from the context of the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your senses are unguarded, pulled out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you're established upon the greater context, the context of the forest, all you need to do is guard your senses on a particular basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, just don't intentionally go with the unwholesome, and context of the forest will be maintained.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Buddha goes further and says, well, what's even greater context than the context of the forest?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if something happens to the forest, which is your context of your mind, then you would be affected.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you go... you look at... you look at the higher.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because context of the forest is greater of the context of any particular village or the town.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you look higher, you can find the context of the earth, planet earth, element of earth, call it whichever way you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you're in the forest, whether you're in a town, whether you're elsewhere, you are on earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's even greater context.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said, if you truly start developing context of the earth, that would require some serious letting go and giving up of, basically, your life and your own body.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, if you're still, like, concerned
[SPEAKER_01]: Over things in your environment, over your kuti, your dwelling, this woodland or that woodland, means you're not giving things up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you then transcend the greater context, when you still refuse to let go of the particular context?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you develop your mind upon the context of Earth, it would result in you not even regarding your own body as belonging to you anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: That truly means developing the greater context, the greater perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why they would encourage it, to contemplate the four elements and so on, because it will result in dispassion towards this particular manifestation of material form on the basis of the greater context of Earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, whenever you... whatever you look in this body, it's... it's the elements that compose everything else in the world, which means all of that is inferior to the great basis of the context of Earth that provides these elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm saying this because sometimes people can think that simply by thinking about the Great Earth, they're developing the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you will know you're developing the context when concern for your own life and body, senses failing, anything that can happen to you, sickness, disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not concerned because your mind is established upon much greater context.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, yeah, that's what I wanted to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could see the context determines the extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to the extent of the perception of the earth, that context defines everything particular that comes your way, and whether you're going to be affected by it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the literal translation, well, the literal Pali word that can be translated as extent, most literally, is casino.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly why the earth casino, the water, fire, air casino,
[SPEAKER_01]: And it would encourage these practices.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you... it's not... usually people think casino practice is staring at the clay pots and red colors and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's developing these perceptions of the context that will have to result in dispassion and abandoning of anything inferior to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, the mind... that the Tathāgata understood the extent of the earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: He understood gratification in earth, danger in earth, and escape in earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is then to be said about everything else that's inferior to Earth?
[SPEAKER_01]: But then he went further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Earth, water, fire, air, the four colors, the infinite space and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said the consciousness is like the most refined of them all.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in the context of simple presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's the suffering that's present, happiness, perception of village, all of it, what it all has in common is it's present.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can discern that extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But by that time, you're virtually going to be, like, full-on arahant, developing, basically, cessation of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't have to...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's enough to do the extent of Earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like progression, you have to go through all ten extents, all ten casinas, all ten contexts.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just start with the lowest one, it will be enough for final liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because in order to properly develop the context of the Earth,
[SPEAKER_01]: that you are partaking in, with your own experience, right here, right now, you will, you will abandon everything inferior to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any sense of ownership in regard to this particular insignificant little body, any like body of others, presences of others, houses, homes, villages, anything, anything, it's inferior to the, to the, to the planet Earth, to the element of Earth that planet Earth is made of.
[SPEAKER_01]: The element of Earth that gives context to the planet Earth, that gives context to the island you're on, mountain you're on, forest you're in, kuti you're sitting in, your own body that you're possessing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see all these great mountains are already greater than your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're going to be here longer than you will.
[SPEAKER_01]: They've been here longer than you ever will be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, it's through not seeing that context,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not allowing it to endure, not knowing how to maintain it, the background of your mind, you get pulled with the particular senses, and then you sort of pervert the whole picture, and then you are the center, you are the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the five modes of being for unenlightened mind are the five contexts, which is the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: The context of sensuality, context of ill-will, restlessness,
[SPEAKER_01]: Doubt and sloth and torpor.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are all contexts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are all general contexts that determine your particular actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able to engage with sensuality, with like, with sensual acts, pursuits, if the context of sensuality is not pushing you that way?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you haven't given in to the pressure of the context of sensuality, would you be then deciding the particular acts towards sensuality?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, at the same time,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were not doing the particular acts of sensuality, would that context be maintained?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, because it needs maintenance.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be engaging in sensuality to be maintaining sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where sensory strain has to come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop maintaining it, so that you can discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, the wholesome context, the context that's on the level of nature of things, it's what the Buddha meant by the extent of the earth, water, fire, air, or these general perceptions that you can use to abandon inferior ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they pertain to the nature of things, as in, they don't require your doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, presence of your body already means presence of the element of earth, by which
[SPEAKER_01]: Which side of that presence you're gonna... you're gonna think about, you're gonna establish yourself, you're gonna be concerned with?
[SPEAKER_01]: The general side of it, which is element of earth is present, that cannot be mine, because how can I own the element of earth?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, the particular manifestation of the element of earth is this body of mine, in which case you will be appropriating it and is regarding it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you start... that's what the Buddha was saying to Rahula, like, be like earth, be like water, not in some poetic sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, because you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: The perception of your own body here contains the greater perception of earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the perception of your own body here, it's inferior to the greater perception of earth in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, the perception of your own body here is on the basis of the context of element of earth, element of solidity, cohesion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fluidity, the four great elements, are the four great characteristics that this particular body has.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, it's other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: These are not characteristics of your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your body is the product of these characteristics.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize you can't own this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't own cohesion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't own solidity.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't own heat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just like ambiguous element of heat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's ambiguous only because you still give priority to the particular result of that context, which is this body of mine and these senses that I can use.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you want to abandon hindrances, you develop greater context.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to abandon hindrance of sloth and torpor?
[SPEAKER_01]: Replace it with a context of something active.
[SPEAKER_01]: Walking back and forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able to move your feet left, right, left, right, left, right, if there is no general intention to walk back and forth, which endures and persists while you keep moving your feet left and right?
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to stop after you move your left foot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or if you're going back and forth, you don't have to go, oh, I'm thinking about behind while I'm going forward, because otherwise I don't know what I'm doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have the context of walking back and forth as one intentional thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what defines all these particular acts you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why... what it carries the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your particular acts that are defined by the context, maintain the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you don't have to keep thinking, I'm walking, I'm walking, I'm walking.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is not forget that you already know that you are walking.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be outside of the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only replace the unwholesome context with wholesome context.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only replace the unwholesome perception of continuity with wholesome perception of continuity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the context endures while you're performing actions on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, replace the context of sensuality with context of restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Context of ill-will with context of loving-kindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Context of doubt with context of comprehension.
[SPEAKER_01]: Context of sloth and torpor with the context of wakefulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: You doing, that's not effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start discerning the context rightly, that's effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because walking maintains the context of walking, but context of walking gives the context to the actual particular movements of your feet and the whole act.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's nothing for you there to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just walking because the context of the walking is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is start discerning the context of the walking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you'll never have a problem doing walking meditation or being lazy for that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is attend to the sign of activity, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: The perception of walking back and forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yes, because it is a form of perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is if you say the perception of walking back and forth,
[SPEAKER_01]: Usually, it just plays into people's misconceived notion of meditation, of I'm perceiving my left foot, my right foot, my left foot, my right foot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, so perception of walking, perception of walking.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, I have to keep telling myself and perceiving that I'm walking in order to know that I'm walking.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you already know that you're walking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you wouldn't be able to walk in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's... that knowledge is that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why mindfulness of the context brings comprehension, brings discernment, brings samādhi, brings composure of that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Context is composed, if it's the right context.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that you can see how it's all basically just completely tied in together.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's mindfulness, context, kasiṇa or samādhi or this, it all leads to the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Clarity of mindfulness and discernment of the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if your walking is determined by the context of the walking, and context of the walking is carried through the walking, where is the room for the sense of self who is saying, I am walking?
[SPEAKER_01]: There isn't any room.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's almost like an automated action, but in only... only way to understand
[SPEAKER_01]: How automated it is, is to abandon your sense of self, through developing this greater context, through discerning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you're either a kutujana, or you're either ārya-sāvaka towards ārahantyu.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have a clear, sort of, step outside from either, and then decide.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're either immersed into not seeing the context, or you start seeing the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the greater context of anicca, anicca, sañña... Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: The context of the nature... What is the nature of things?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's context of those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the dhamma is the universal context.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what's most universal about anything, good, bad, far, near, personal, impersonal?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that it has a reason on its own, that cannot provide that lasting satisfaction of ownership, and because of that, cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's anicca, it's that universal context, one of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unsatisfactoriness is another universal context.
[SPEAKER_01]: The result of these universal contexts, contexts says, is that your experience is experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this cannot belong to me, because it's it's determined by this greater context, which I'm not saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, how can you own a notion of cohesion?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you own
[SPEAKER_01]: Solidity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fluidity.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, see, you see this fluidity, solidity, cohesion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see that secondary to the sense of self, because you haven't developed the right context in regard to your sense of self, on account of which you would have discerned these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the four great elements, the four great contexts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, yeah, you could approach it through the contemplation,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, rather than seeing something change, I get up and I sit down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, that's that's on the level of inferior perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not seeing the context there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense,
[SPEAKER_01]: When I said that perception of the forest doesn't work, if you think that perception of the forest is, oh, I'm perceiving the forest, I'm perceiving the forest, I'm perceiving the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if perception of the change is what anicca is, then you would have to die in order to give up your life, as an arahant would give up his life through understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Give up attachment to the life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can you perceive... how can you give up death if the only way to give up that is perceiving you dying?
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you have to basically be dead to become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it doesn't matter what you do throughout your life because death will make you an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the contrary, it's the presence of the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that presence, you get to discern anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, anicca is not a perception of change.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anicca is basically perception of I cannot own this even if I want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a perception of this is against me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a perception of independent of me, yet I depend on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically putting that which you've been putting second, as first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And putting that which you've been putting as first, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: my sense of self, as second.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if sense of self is second, then it's on myself anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it...
[SPEAKER_01]: In order for it to be maintained itself, needs to be primary, needs to be the center of my experience, needs to be mine, needs to be master, needs to be in control.
[SPEAKER_00]: That nature of anicca, the great, the great context of anicca, that's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If one sees, one sees that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Context is not like this, it's not a, it's not an objective thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to know what to look for in order to discern.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you have, like, infinite amount of contexts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they're determined by what you're looking for.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why instruction of another, the right instruction of somebody, this sotāpanna or higher, or ideally the Buddha himself, is required.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you will not be discerning this context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you manage to discern this context on your own, context of anicca, you become samasambuddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the most universal context is the context that the dhamma is laid upon.
[SPEAKER_01]: The dhamma is total.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to know what to look for.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to know what signs and tokens to start discerning to develop the perception of the greater context.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, yeah, the most great context is, I can't own anything even if I want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that context becomes your mode of being
[SPEAKER_01]: Through the clarity of comprehension you developed in regard to it, nothing particular will be able to sway you, or perturb you, or disturb you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't own, already, this own body of yours, let alone anything that can come through these senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: It all becomes even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what... how the Buddha said that if you develop money in regard to the extent, the casino, you would abandon things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you'd abandon the things in regard to the great perception of the, like, casino of Earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he said, what is to be said about everything inferior to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that... that cannot even... like, this cannot bother me anymore, let alone anything inferior to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you truly understood,
[SPEAKER_01]: The most fundamental context of anicca, in regard to everything that has a nature to manifest, that's basically sotāpatti.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it means.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever has the context of arising, because of that, has the context of cessation, has the context of non-ownership, non-appropriation, indifference, dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these other contexts come from that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: But how can you discern a context?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't even start having an idea of the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: No instruction, no reflection, no questioning, no interrogation, no looking for the meaning of the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: When all you do is look at the particular thing that's in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sight, sight, sound, sound, smell, smell, taste, taste, touch, touch, sitting, sitting, walking, left, right, back, forward, left, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a... Basically, it's a... it's a... Well, I'm sure many people are not aware of it, but in practice, it becomes like a... like a cop-out.
[SPEAKER_01]: You try to overcome the context of suffering, context of non-enlightenment, through denying that there is a context at all, through focusing and staring as hard as you can at what's right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when there is in front, you don't think about back.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it's back, you don't think about being in the present moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's usually what people mean by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Focus, focus to the one point whereby you forget everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that kind of temporary oblivion in regard to the context feels like freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not a lasting freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if there is not a lasting freedom, how can you say it's free?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you say I'm free, when somebody else, something else, dictates my time of freedom?
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you're not free.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just get a little bit of a break from your imprisonment.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only true way of freedom is to understand, what did Buddha say?
[SPEAKER_01]: Nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you understand the nature of things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just by understanding what's most universal in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's most universal in anything that manifests?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's a universal thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has manifested on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that, it cannot provide my pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were to understand the dhamma, the meaning of the dhamma, just by looking, just by listening, just by touching, just by sitting, moving, touching, whatever else,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the Buddha would have said so.
[SPEAKER_01]: He would be talking about all these ways of establishing your mind, discerning the nature of things, and not resting until there's like... until you're sure in your knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, not just the knowledge, the knowledge that you know as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could see that practically, when people end up practicing the focusing meditation to one point, it's all done
[SPEAKER_01]: From the context of trying to deny, ignore, get rid of the greater context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because greater context is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why a person who invested a lot of their time and energy and years in this kind of concentration practice, becomes very uneasy.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that concentration practice is compromised or questioned, or even just challenged by somebody, not even at them, just... they might read something what somebody said and dismisses it, and they would be affected existentially.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would feel need to defend it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they become aware, unwillingly, of the greater context.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is the most fundamental nature of the greater context?
[SPEAKER_01]: Any context, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's manifested, it's there, cannot be owned, cannot provide lasting satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize then that, ironically, for many people, practice of dhamma, through that concentration, meditation, object and technique, takes them away from the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because dhamma is nowhere in the context, not running away from it and covering it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the danger of the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can think... you can be thinking you're doing the dhamma rightly, while in reality you're just developing your wrong views further and further and further.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's easy to uproot.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, the longer you don't do it, the more courage to do it you're gonna need.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the point will come when, theoretically, the courage will be possible, but practically becomes impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will do it just if you have the courage to ask yourself, okay, if I were to drop
[SPEAKER_01]: All my knowledge, all my techniques, everything I've been doing in my life, would I be able to suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would I be affected by suffering in the first place?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, I might have a perfect meditation technique, and perfect management, and my teacher always tells me what I need to hear.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all great.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I've been celebrating, practicing this for 45, 50 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, put all that aside.
[SPEAKER_01]: If suffering were to arise, of any kind, shape or form, for whatever reason, would you be affected first?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, would you have to do all of these things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you just need to do them for a second, still, would your doing be a response to being affected by suffering in the first place?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did your practice make you completely, completely imperturbable?
[SPEAKER_01]: If the answer is yes, great, carry on.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the answer is no, there you go, that's your work there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean that everything that has been done was complete waste, but you'll find that out only afterwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you free yourself from suffering, then you'll see what you've been doing was wasteful and what wasn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only method of discerning context is learning where the context is, and then making an effort to discern it.